Guide to the Asa Burton Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Asa Burton papers
1781-1973
1781-1829
MS 1421
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
0.25
(1 box)
The papers of Asa Burton, Congregational minister and theologian, consist of religious, autobiographical, and historical writings. Several of the essays record the religious, social, and political history of Thetford, Vermont, particularly the rise of political parties. The papers also include a published version of Burton's memoirs (1973).
Burton, Asa, 1752-1836
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Ruth Adams in 1954. The papers were originally part of the Miscellaneous Manuscripts Collection, MS 352.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Associated Materials
Additional Asa Burton manuscripts are at Vassar College.
Scope and Contents
The Asa Burton Papers consist of sermons and writings, which document Burton's service to the Congregational church in Thetford, Vermont, and contain observations on his life and church and town history. The papers contain an autobiographical memoir as well as essays on Thetford's society and politics. Burton records the developing political tensions between Federalists and Republicans and the manner in which the chruch and its mnister were drawn into political strife. It contains Burton's exposition of a chruch trial involving political partisans Beriah Loomis and Asher Chamberlain. Burton's sermons on the anniversaries of his twenty-fifth and fiftieth year in the ministry and other special occasions are also included in the papers. Material from some folders is transcribed in published edtion of Burton's memoirs and writings, edied by Charles Latham Jr.
The Burton manuscripts were donated to the Yale University Library by Ruth Adams in 1954. They were transferred frm the Miscellaneous Manuscripts Collection (MS 352) in 1985. Additional Burton papers were given to Vassar College.
Biographical / Historical
Asa Burton was born in Stonington, Connecticut, and, at age 16, moved to Norwich, Vermont. In 1777 he graduated from Dartmouth and was ordained in 1779 at Thetford, Vermont, where he became pastor for life. Burton was best known as a teacher of theology.
Congregational churches -- Clergy; Religion and politics -- Vermont; Thetford (Vt.: Town) -- History; Memoirs; Sermons; Clergy; Burton, Asa, 1752-1836
- Inventory
  - Burton, Asa
    - "An answer to a paper signed by 88 names containing charges agains the Revd. Asa Burton", [ca. 1818] (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - "A brief history of the beginnings, progress, and increase of political parties in Thetford down to the year 1815" (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - "A concise history of the church & society in Thetford...", [1823?] (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - "The confession of faith," with names of church members (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - "The confession of faith of the church in Thetford amended...", 1821
    - "The defence of the church...", [ca. 1815] (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - "The doings of the convention at churches held at Thetford", 1781
    - "The life of Asa Burton written by himself", 1817 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - "...my further additions to the history of my life.." (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Sermons, 1795, 1804, 1813, 1817, 1829 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Latham, Charles Jr.
    - "The life of Asa Burton written by himself", 1973 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - "A short history of Thetford, Vermont, 1761-1870", 1972 (Box 1, Folder 10)